The Life Of Muhammadﷺ, Madinan Period Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا إِنَّمَا الْمُشْرِكُونَ نَجَسٌ فَلَا يَقْرَبُوا الْمَسْجِدَ الْحَرَامَ بَعْدَ عَامِهِمْ هَٰذَا
وَإِنْ خِفْتُمْ عَيْلَةً فَسَوْفَ يُغْنِيكُمُ اللَّهُ مِنْ فَضْلِهِ إِنْ شَاءَ ۚ
إِنَّ اللَّهَ عَلِيمٌ حَكِيمٌ۝
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says: O you, who have believed, indeed the polytheists are unclean.
So, let them not approach Al-Masjid Al-Haram(ألمسجد الحرام), after this, their final year
and if you fear privation, Allah will enrich you from His bounty, if He wills
indeed Allah is Knowing and Wise.
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) for centuries, their livelihood was based on doing business.
They had an influx of people coming in for Hajj(حج) and Umrah(عمره), throughout the year.
So, that was the foundation of their business.
So, what they used to do is buy and trade with the people,
who are coming in to Makkah throughout the year.
That's all what they knew, how to do, they weren't into anything else.
Rasool Allah ﷺ announced to the Mushrikeen(مشركين) that after this year, and this was in the ninth year of Hijrah(هجرة),
No Mushrik(مشرك) is allowed into Al-Masjid Al-Haram(ألمسجد الحرام)!
No Mushrik(مشرك) is allowed into Masjid Al-Haram(ألمسجد الحرام), into Makkah.
To the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) this was the catastrophe, the disaster, we're dead.
Because not all of the Arabs have become Muslim yet.
Yani(يعني) Najd(نجد) and all of those areas are not yet Muslim, you have Al-Hijaaz(الحجاز) is already Muslim,
but the other parts of Arabia have not accepted Islam yet.
So, the bulk of the Arabian Peninsula have not become Muslim.
And these are the ones, who are going to come in and do Hajj(حج) and do Umrah(عمره).
And these are the ones whom we depend on, for our livelihood.
And now, Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying that they're banned from entering the country.
I mean, this is not good for the economy.
And by the way, not only today are people thinking about the economy,
even then economy, financial resources was a major concern of the people.
And a lot of the decisions that the politicians make are based on economical reasons.
So, the people of Quraish(قريش), were thinking in economical terms
and saying that this is not a wise decision.
How are we going to live?
And this is the Ayah(آية) that we just recited, Allahعَزّوجَلّ saying,
O, you have believed indeed the polytheist are unclean.
That's reasoning behind the banning of Mushrikeen(ألمشركين) from entering into Al-Haram(الحرم).
The Ayah(آية) is saying that the reason why, they're not allowed in.?
Is because of their Nijasa(نجاسة).
And then Allah says: So, let them not approach Al-Masjid Al-Haram(ألمسجد الحرام) after this.
It's their final year Khalaas(خلاص), this is the last year,
and this announcement was made in the ninth year of Hijrah(هجرة).
And as a response to the complaints of the people, of Quraish(قريش), they are already Muslim.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says and if you fear, privation,
Allah will enrich you from His bounty, if He wills.
Indeed Allah is Knowing and Wise.
And this is Tawakkal(توكل) in Allahعَزّوجَلّ, if something is Haram(حرام), we stop from it.
If something is Halaal(حلال), we encourage people to do it.
That is how we base our decisions.
It's not on what will make us money and what will not.
So, Islam came to change the way people think, because people usually think in financial terms,
and decisions are made laws are made, in that sense.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling them, if you have trust in Allahعَزّوجَلّ, Allah will provide for you.
And it was difficult thing for Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
because, they didn't have any other skill or art to do and make money.
I mean, the land in Makkah is not suitable for planting anything.
It's very infertile dry land, rocky tracks and no rain.
So, when business was their only job that they knew how to do,
and they're told not to do it, they were kind of concerned, they were worried.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ told them Allah will provide for you, Khalas(خلاص).
Allah will provide for you.
Let's have Eeman(إيمان) in Allahعَزّوجَلّ let's do what Allahعَزّوجَلّ told us.
And by the way, brothers, and sisters, this has many implications on us today,
because there are a lot of Muslims, who deal with Ribaa(رباء), who sell Haraam(حرام) things
and the reason is, this is the only way we can make money.
So, they open a grocery store, and they sell things that are Haraam(حرام),
you tell them this is Haraam(حرام), they say how are we going to live?
And then you find people buying houses using mortgages,
which is a clear Ribaa(رباء) without any doubts.
And then they say, how are we going to survive,
we're going to lose all of our money, if we keep on paying rent.
The response to these people is;
وَمَنْ يَتَّقِ اللَّهَ يَجْعَلْ لَهُ مَخْرَجًا۝وَيَرْزُقْهُ مِنْ حَيْثُ لَا يَحْتَسِبُ
Whoever has Taqwa(تقوى), Allah will find a way out for them
and will provide them from sources they never expected.
It's a promise from Allahعَزّوجَلّ, if you have Taqwa(تقوى) and you believe in Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
then this is, what will happen Allah will provide for you.
Put your trust in Allahعَزّوجَلّ and Allah will provide for you.
So, how does Allah provide for the people of Makkah?
The next Ayah(آية) verse 29.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
قَاتِلُوا الَّذِينَ لَا يُؤْمِنُونَ بِاللَّهِ وَلَا بِالْيَوْمِ الْآخِرِ وَلَا
وَلَا يُحَرِّمُونَ مَا حَرَّمَ اللَّهُ وَرَسُولُهُ وَلَا يَدِينُونَ دِينَ الْحَقِّ مِنَ الَّذِينَ أُوتُوا الْكِتَابَ حَتَّىٰ
حَتَّىٰ يُعْطُوا الْجِزْيَةَ عَنْ يَدٍ وَهُمْ صَاغِرُونَ۝
Fight those, who do not believe in Allah, or in the last day,
and who do not consider unlawful what Allah and His Messenger have made unlawful,
and who do not adopt the religion of truth from those who're given the Scripture,
fight until, they give the Jizya(جزيه) willingly while they are humbled.
This is how Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) starts the chapter on the events of the ninth year of Hijrah(هجرة).
And this is how he opens, his section on the Battle of Tabook(تبوك),
it is by giving a brief Tafseer(تفسير) of these two Ayaat(آيات).
The order from Allahعَزّوجَلّ in verse 123, of Surah Taubah(سورة توبة), Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا قَاتِلُوا الَّذِينَ يَلُونَكُمْ مِنَ الْكُفَّارِ وَلْيَجِدُوا فِيكُمْ غِلْظَةً
وَاعْلَمُوا أَنَّ اللَّهَ مَعَ الْمُتَّقِينَ۝
O, you, who have believed! Fight those, adjacent to you, of the disbelievers
and let them find in you harshness and know that Allah is with the righteous.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says, fight those adjacent to you.
Who are the ones adjacent to the Muslims now, in the ninth year of Hijrah(هجرة)?
It is the Romans.
Because the Roman Empire reaches to the boundary of Hijaaz(حجاز).
So, the first people who are included in this Ayah(آية) are the Romans,
because when this is Ayah(آية) was revealed all of the Arabs of Hijaaz(حجاز), were Muslim.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ started the greatest mobilization ever, in the history of Islam, so far.
Rasool Allah ﷺ usually, when he would lead an army or send out an army,
he would maintain secrecy of the target, in order to ambush the enemy and take them by surprise.
However, in this incident, Rasool Allah ﷺ made it public from day one.
Why?
First of all, because they're facing a new enemy, they are facing the Roman Empire.
And you know this is a different situation here.
Here now, we're not facing a tribe
and we're not facing people from our own kind, whom we already know.
This is something that is unknown.
It is a foreign nation.
Plus, the Roman Empire has such a great reputation all over the world, for its strength and power.
And this reputation is centuries old,
Therefore Rasool Allah ﷺ made it clear from the beginning that we are going to fight Ar-Rome(ألروم).
The next, second reason is because of the distance,
there's gonna be a lot of traveling involved,
and therefore, Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted them to prepare accordingly.
I mean, this is not a short distance travel, and therefore a lot of preparation is needed.
And the third reason, it was the worst time of the year to travel, it was mid-summer, very hot.
And it was the time when the dates are ripening on the palm trees.
And that's a very tempting time to stay behind
because the life of the people of Madina was based on agriculture
and their agriculture was pretty much mostly palm dates, that was the main agriculture of the people of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
So, you wait all year long for the harvest.
And now, we're supposed to travel right at that time when the fruit is ripening on the tree, and it's very tempting.
So, it was a very difficult time to set out.
But the Battle of Tabook(تبوك) is going to be the last major trial
that the Muslims are going to go through before the death of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And you will notice that the Battle of Tabook(تبوك) represents the peak of Islam,
and represents the most difficult test so far.
And it was the Battle of Tabook(تبوك) that brought down the Ayaat(آيات) that are talking about the Nifaaq(نفاق) and Eeman(إيمان).
So, this was going to be the criteria between the true believers and the Munafiqeen(منافقين),
this is a closing chapter in the Jihad(جهاد), of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, now the final laws of fighting are going to come.
These are the Ayaat(آيات) that will abrogate the Ayaat(آيات) before.
And the Ayaat(آيات) that will expose the Munafiqeen(منافقين) are going to come down in Tabook(تبوك),
even though the phenomena of Nifaaq(نفاق) is a few years old by now
because Nifaaq(نفاق) appeared in Madina, right after the Battle of Badr(بدر).
So, we're talking about a span of seven years of the existence of the Nifaaq(نفاق).
Nevertheless, the Surah(سورة) that talk the most about Nifaaq(نفاق) is the Surah(سورة) of At-Taubah(ألتوبة).
And Surah At-Taubah(سورة التوبة) was revealed in the ninth year of Hijrah(هجرة),
which was the year in which the battle of Tabook(تبوك) occurred.
And most of the Ayaat(آيات) of Surah At-Taubah(سورة التوبة) are relating to the Battle of Tabook(تبوك).
So, these are prime moments, very important moments.
And we're getting close to the end of the Daw'ah(دعوة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, what we're talking about now, brothers and sisters are the final stages.
What we're talking about now are the final chapters.
And they are the final and most important ones.
I mean, this is even though in the Battle of Tabook(تبوك).
There was no fighting, but it was an epic event.
It has such an importance in Shariah(شريعة), and in Seerah(سيرة) and in Aqeedah(عقيدة)
in every aspect of Islamic knowledge.
And that's why we'll be going through a lot of Ayaat(آيات)
because there are so many Ayaat(آيات) that were revealed in Surah At-Taubah(سورة التوبة) of about the Battle of Tabook(تبوك).
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ said:
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا قَاتِلُوا الَّذِينَ يَلُونَكُمْ مِنَ الْكُفَّارِ وَلْيَجِدُوا فِيكُمْ غِلْظَةً ۚ وَاعْلَمُوا أَنَّ اللَّهَ مَعَ الْمُتَّقِينَ۝
O you, who have believed, fight those adjacent to you of the disbelievers
and let them find in you harshness and know that Allah is with the righteous.
So again, the battle Tabook(تبوك) represents a trial from Allahعَزّوجَلّ
because again, as I mentioned, there was no fighting involved.
But it was a test, and it represented the most difficult battle so far.
And that is the reason why? This battle was given the name Jaish Al Usra(جيش ألعسره),
the army of difficulty.
Usrah(عسره) means difficult, severe, tough,
because the financing of the army was difficult,
the Gathering of the army was difficult,
the travel of the army was difficult,
the weather was difficult,
and the enemy that they're facing is difficult.
And that's why it's called the Battle of difficulty,
Jaish Al-Usrah(جيش ألعسره), or the army of difficulty.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ has called it in Qur'an Sa'ah Tul Usrah(ساعة العسره),
the hour of difficulty and we'll get to that Ayah(آية), In sha Allah(اِنْ شاءالله).
THE MOBILIZATION;
Rasool Allah ﷺ called the people, who're in Madina, and the surrounding tribes, and Makkah, all over, all of the Muslims.
There was never such a mobilization before.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to recruit every able bodied Muslim.
And the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an, came to support this and to lay down the final laws regarding fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in verse 38, Surah At-Taubah(سورة التوبة).
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا مَا لَكُمْ إِذَا قِيلَ لَكُمُ انْفِرُوا فِي سَبِيلِ اللَّهِ اثَّاقَلْتُمْ إِلَى الْأَرْضِ
أَرَضِيتُمْ بِالْحَيَاةِ الدُّنْيَا مِنَ الْآخِرَةِ ۚ فَمَا مَتَاعُ الْحَيَاةِ الدُّنْيَا فِي الْآخِرَةِ إِلَّا قَلِيلٌ۝
The call was difficult,
and therefore people were finding it hard convincing themselves to come out.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ in this Ayah(آية), and you see brothers and sisters Qur'an speaks to the heart.
And it exposes the heart and tells you the illness that is in the heart, whether you know it or not.
And that is something unique about Qur'an
because it is from Allahعَزّوجَلّ, it is the word of Allahعَزّوجَلّ, it is from the One, Who created you
and knows what is good for you and what is bad
and knows what is happening in the inner, in your heart of heart, what is happening inside.
And these are things that you might not even recognize yourself, within yourself.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling the people the reason why, they do not want to go out.?
Because you see, people might give many reasons,
they might say because the Fiqh(فقه) does not state we have to go out.
Some might say because there is a difference of opinion,
some might say because it doesn't make sense.
Some might say because it's not it's not wise.
But Allahعَزّوجَلّ tells them why?
O you, who have believed, what is the matter with you,
that when you are told to go forth in the cause of Allah, you adhere heavily to Earth,
that is the reason it is love of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), it is adherence to the earth.
Are you satisfied with the life of this world rather than the hereafter.
But what is the enjoyment of worldly life compared to the hereafter, except a very little.
So, this Ayah(آية) mentions the cause, and it mentions the cure,
it mentions the disease and the cure.
The disease is, attachment to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
اثَّاقَلْتُمْ إِلَى الْأَرْضِ
You are adhering to Earth.
You love your life, and you don't want to leave it behind.
And the cure is
Allahعَزّوجَلّ is reminding us with the reality of this world
that it is nothing compared to the hereafter.
And from day one, this Ayah(آية) is in At-Toubah(ألتوبة),
the first Ayaat(آيات) which were in Surah Al-Baqarah(سورة ألبقره), where the command to fight with was given.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
كُتِبَ عَلَيْكُمُ الْقِتَالُ وَهُوَ كُرْهٌ لَكُمْ
Fighting has been prescribed on you, while you dislike it.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ told us: This is something that we dislike.
We even not only dislike to do, we dislike to talk about it.
And look at it right now, how many people are talking about this,
even though it is one of the Faraidh(فرائض) in Islam,
even though there are so many Ayaat(آيات) and so many Ahadith(أحاديث) talking about this,
but people don't want to speak about it, let alone do it.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling us what the disease is and giving us the cure.
And then Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling us what will happen if we don't fight in His sake.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
إِلَّا تَنْفِرُوا يُعَذِّبْكُمْ عَذَابًا أَلِيمًا وَيَسْتَبْدِلْ قَوْمًا غَيْرَكُمْ وَلَا تَضُرُّوهُ شَيْئًا ۗ
وَاللَّهُ عَلَىٰ كُلِّ شَيْءٍ قَدِيرٌ۝
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says: If you do not go forth, He will punish you with a painful punishment.
And our condition today is a testimony to this.
Look at how we are being punished because we're staying behind.
We are poor even though we are the wealthiest
our land and what is beneath our land is wealthy.
Nevertheless, we're poor.
We are disunited even though we should be the most United Ummah(امة).
We are weak when we should be the highest and strongest Ummah(امة).
All of this is punishment from Allahعَزّوجَلّ because we did not give support to His Deen(دين).
If you do not go forth, He will punish you with a painful punishment
and will replace you with another people
and you will not harm Him at all and Allah is over all things competent.
So, this is the punishment of Allah and Allah is warning the Muslims
because as I said many of them do not like talking about this, let alone doing it.
In fact not only talking about it, they don't even want hear about it,
and then Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
إِلَّا تَنْصُرُوهُ فَقَدْ نَصَرَهُ اللَّهُ
إِذْ أَخْرَجَهُ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا ثَانِيَ اثْنَيْنِ إِذْ هُمَا فِي الْغَارِ إِذْ يَقُولُ لِصَاحِبِهِ
إِذْ يَقُولُ لِصَاحِبِهِ لَا تَحْزَنْ إِنَّ اللَّهَ مَعَنَا
فَأَنْزَلَ اللَّهُ سَكِينَتَهُ عَلَيْهِ وَأَيَّدَهُ بِجُنُودٍ لَمْ تَرَوْهَا
وَجَعَلَ كَلِمَةَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا السُّفْلَىٰ ۗ وَكَلِمَةُ اللَّهِ هِيَ الْعُلْيَا ۗ
وَاللَّهُ عَزِيزٌ حَكِيمٌ۝
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says; If you do not aid the Prophet, Allah has already aided him.
If we do not defend Rasool Allah ﷺ,
if we do not defend the honor of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
if we do not protect him,
Rasool Allah ﷺ does not need us, Allahعَزّوجَلّ will protect him.
It is something that we need to do for our own sake for our own benefit.
But Allahعَزّوجَلّ will support His messenger.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says; Allah has already aided him,
when those who disbelieve had driven him out of Makkah as one of two, he and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) in the Hijrah(هجرة).
When they were in the cave and he said to his companion, do not grieve Rasool Ullah speaking to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Do not grieve indeed Allah is with us,
and Allah sent down his tranquility upon him
and supported him with angels, you did not see and made the word of those, who disbelieved, the lowest,
while the word of Allah that is the highest, and Allah is exalted in Might and Wise.
And then Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
اِنْفِرُوا خِفَافًا وَثِقَالًا وَجَاهِدُوا بِأَمْوَالِكُمْ
وَجَاهِدُوا بِأَمْوَالِكُمْ وَأَنْفُسِكُمْ فِي سَبِيلِ اللَّهِ ۚ
ذَٰلِكُمْ خَيْرٌ لَكُمْ إِنْ كُنْتُمْ تَعْلَمُونَ۝
Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling the Sahabah(صحابه) and telling us and telling every Muslim.
Go forth, Whether light or heavy and strive with your wealth and your lives in the cause of Allah.
That is better for you, if you only knew.
اِنْفِرُوا خِفَافًا وَثِقَالًا
Go forth, whether light or heavy! What does light or heavy mean?
Al-Qurtabi(ألقرطبي) mentions the opinions of the scholars of Tafseer(تفسير).
They said: Young and old, busy or not busy, wealthy or poor, everyone needs to go out.
When this Ayah(آية) was revealed the Sahabah(صحابه) viewed this, as such a burden,
they said: That no one has an excuse everybody has to go out.
And that is when Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed the Ayah(آية) ;
لَيْسَ عَلَى الضُّعَفَاءِ وَلَا عَلَى الْمَرْضَىٰ وَلَا عَلَى الَّذِينَ لَا يَجِدُونَ مَا يُنْفِقُونَ
لَا يَجِدُونَ مَا يُنْفِقُونَ حَرَجٌ إِذَا نَصَحُوا لِلَّهِ وَرَسُولِهِ
مَا عَلَى الْمُحْسِنِينَ مِنْ سَبِيلٍ ۚ
وَاللَّهُ غَفُورٌ رَحِيمٌ۝
There is not upon the weak, or upon the ill, or upon those who do not find anything to spend,
any discomfort when they are sincere to Allah and His messenger.
There is not upon the doers of good any cause for blame and Allah is Forgiving and Merciful.
So, Allah excused the weak and the ill and the ones who do not find anything to spend.
Otherwise everyone else needs to go out.
I mean, Abu Qatadah(ابو قتادة), the knight of Rasool Ullah رضي الله عنه,
he was seen on it horse
and he was such an old man that his eyebrows were covering his eyes.
And he was by then, he gained a lot of weight.
So, he was told that you are among the ones who're excused, why are you going out?
He said the Surah(سورة) of At-Taubah(ألتوبة) has left us no excuse.
That was the understanding of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ is saying go forth with light and heavy
and then Allah says and strive with your wealth and your lives.
Notice here that the wealth was mentioned before the lives and that is how it is in every Ayah(آية).
Except in one Ayah(آية) in Qur'an.
And that is because fighting consumes money.
I mean, it just burns it away.
That was the case then and that's the case now.
I mean, fighting any war effort just swallows up money and that is why.?
Allahعَزّوجَلّ in the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an and Rasool Allah ﷺ in the Ahadith(أحاديث)
emphasized on the importance of spending Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(في سبيل الله).
In fact Al-Qurtabi(ألقرطبي) says, that every other Sadaqah(صدقه) is multiplied by 10.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ says that
اَلْحَسَنَةْ بِعَشَرَةْ اَمثالِهَا
One good deed is multiplied by 10.
Except when you spend in the path of Allah it is equivalent to 700 because of the Ayah(آية) in Surat Ul Baqarah(سورة البقره)
that talks about the grain that multiplies into 700.
And that is when it is  spent in Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(في سبيل الله).
And Ibn Al-Hajar(إبن حجر) says that whenever Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) is mentioned,
it usually means the context of Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(في سبيل الله),
and therefore Al-Qurtabi(ألقرطبي) says that
every other spending whether it is for the poor, or the needy, or building a Masjid(مسجد) or whatever
1 dollar or one, whatever currency it is, is multiplied by 10,
while when it is for the fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), one equals 700.
And that is to emphasize the importance of spending because it's such an expensive thing.
I mean, it just incinerate money.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ started fundraising, collecting the donations,
He would stand up and ask the people to give
and it was a difficult time in terms of the financial resources of the people that didn't have much,
especially that is before the harvest and that is where their money is.
But they were still bringing Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) brought his money and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب)
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ was asking for more,
So Uthman Ibn Affan رضي الله عنه brought a 100 camels ready with their saddles and all, the whole thing.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ asked for more Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان بن عفان) brought 100
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ asked for more, so he brought 100
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ asked for more, so Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان بن عفان) brought some gold coins,
and they poured it, in the lap of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Rasool Allah was had his fingers in these coins and
I mean, they were in his lap and his fingers were in the coins. And Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مَا ضَرَّ عُثْمَان مَا فَعَلَ بَعْدَ الْيَوْمَ
Nothing Uthman(عثمان) does after this day, would harm him.
Whatever he does, that's it, he is forgiven, because of what he has done on this day.
And this shows you the virtue of spending Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Then there were those, who are looking for excuses to get out of their duties.
And let's read the Ayaat(آيات) that talk about them. Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَإِذَا أُنْزِلَتْ سُورَةٌ أَنْ آمِنُوا بِاللَّهِ وَجَاهِدُوا مَعَ رَسُولِهِ
اسْتَأْذَنَكَ أُولُو الطَّوْلِ مِنْهُمْ وَقَالُوا ذَرْنَا نَكُنْ مَعَ الْقَاعِدِينَ۝
رَضُوا بِأَنْ يَكُونُوا مَعَ الْخَوَالِفِ وَطُبِعَ عَلَىٰ قُلُوبِهِمْ فَهُمْ لَا يَفْقَهُونَ۝
And when a Surah(سورة) was revealed, enjoining them to believe in Allah
and to fight with His messenger, those of wealth among them, ask your permission to stay back and said;
Leave us to be with them, who sit at home.
And who are these, who are asking to be excused.?
They are the ones with wealth,
so the exact ones, who should be going out are the exact ones, who are asking for an excuse to stay,
and this shows us the Fitnah(فِتْنَه) of money.
I mean, money in itself is not evil.
But if it causes a person to forsake their duties towards Allah and His religion,
then it becomes an evil instrument.
And here in this Ayah(آية) we find that these people came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
"We don't want to go, Excuse us!" Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
رَضُوا بِأَنْ يَكُونُوا مَعَ الْخَوَالِفِ وَطُبِعَ عَلَىٰ قُلُوبِهِمْ فَهُمْ لَا يَفْقَهُونَ۝
They were satisfied to be with those who stay behind, women and children.
And their hearts were sealed over, so they do not understand.
Pay attention to this, these people have heard Qur'an.
And these are people, who sat in, the Khut'bah(خطبه) and the lectures of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
so most likely, they know more than me and you
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ says about them: La Yafqahoon(لا يفقهون).
They have no understanding.
People who heard Qur'an fresh from the heavens,
and heard the Hadith(حديث) not from a book, but from the mouth of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and lived in the context, you see,
they lived in the context of when the verses were revealed, and when they Hadith(حديث) was said.
So, no matter how much we read,
we will not reach to that understanding, because we were not there.
And still Allah says that they do not understand.
By today's standards, they would be great scholars, but they do not understand.
Why.? Because they don't get the point.
They do not understand the reality of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and Akhirah(آخرة),
they do not understand the wisdom behind Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(في سبيل الله),
they do not understand the importance of sacrifice, they just don't get it.
And many are the Muslims today who don't get it, who don't understand the proper Islamic view of the world.
And they do not understand the issue of the importance of supporting the Deen(دين) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
So, understanding brothers and sisters is not how many Ayaat(آيات) and how many Ahadith(أحاديث) you memorize and you know,
understanding is the Fiqh(فقه) of the heart, the understanding of the heart.
Because anybody can memorize Qur'an and Hadith(حديث), even a non Muslim could do that.
I mean, there are Islamic Studies departments in many universities, in the West and other parts of the world.
And many of the students who get the top grades over there are non Muslim.
So, they know Ahadith(احاديث) and they know Ayaat(آيات), so is that the criteria of true knowledge? No.
True Knowledge is not how much Ayaat(آيات) and Ahadith(احاديث) you have learned.
But how much do you understand them and follow them.
Because if you are just memorizing Ayaat(آيات) and Ahadith(احاديث)
you're just adding up evidence against you on the Day of Judgment,
because every Ayah(آية) that you know will be an evidence against you, on the Day Of Judgment,
you're actually making it worse for yourself.
And every Hadith(حديث) that you learn will be evidence against you because you knew it,
and he didn't follow it and you did nothing.
So, actually, you're worse than somebody who didn't know it.
Because the one who didn't know it, can say on the Day of Judgment.
O Allah I never knew about this, nobody told me about it.
But the one who knows it has no excuse at all.
And these people knew the truth and they didn't follow it.
So, the Fiqh(فقه), and this is very important.
Don't be deceived, by sweet tongue.
And don't be deceived by people, who have wrote, they just memorize everything and they just spit it out to you.
But it's, you should take the example by the ones, who are following the Haqq(حق),
not the ones who are just saying it.
The ones, who are saying it, if they're saying the Haqq(حق) than follow it yourself,
then Allahعَزّوجَلّ says, about the ones who understand.
لَٰكِنِ الرَّسُولُ وَالَّذِينَ آمَنُوا مَعَهُ جَاهَدُوا بِأَمْوَالِهِمْ وَأَنْفُسِهِمْ
وَأُولَٰئِكَ لَهُمُ الْخَيْرَاتُ ۖ وَأُولَٰئِكَ هُمُ الْمُفْلِحُونَ۝
But the messenger and those, who believed with him, fought with their wealth and their lives.
Those will have all that is good and it is those who are successful.
أَعَدَّ اللَّهُ لَهُمْ جَنَّاتٍ تَجْرِي مِنْ تَحْتِهَا الْأَنْهَارُ خَالِدِينَ فِيهَا ۚ ذَٰلِكَ الْفَوْزُ الْعَظِيمُ۝
Allah has prepared for them gardens beneath, which rivers flow,
where in they will abide eternally, that is the great attainment.
Then Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَجَاءَ الْمُعَذِّرُونَ مِنَ الْأَعْرَابِ لِيُؤْذَنَ لَهُمْ وَقَعَدَ الَّذِينَ كَذَبُوا اللَّهَ وَرَسُولَهُ ۚ
And those with excuses among the Bedouins came to be permitted to remain.
These are some Bedouins who had valid excuses.
They came to Rasool Allah ﷺ, according to some Mufassireen(مفسرين), they say they have valid excuses,
and some of them say that they didn't.
There's a difference of opinion on the exact meaning of this part of the Ayah(آية),
but then Allahعَزّوجَلّ says and they who had lied to Allah and His Messenger sat at home.
سَيُصِيبُ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا مِنْهُمْ عَذَابٌ أَلِيمٌ۝
There will strike those, who disbelieved are among them, a painful punishment.
Now, we recited this Ayah(آية) the ones, who are excused from going out.
There is not upon the weak or upon the ill or upon those, who do not find anything to spend,
any discomfort when they are sincere to Allah and His Messenger,
there is not upon the doers of good any cause for blame and Allah is forgiving and merciful.
The next Ayah(آية), talks about some of the Sahabah(صحابه),
who came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and they said: O Rasool Allah carry us,
meaning provide us with transportation, we have nothing.
Because part of the preparation is that you need to have your camel or your horse to travel.
This is the long distance, you can't just go without any preparation.
So, these were very poor Sahabah(صحابه), but they sincerely want to go.
So, they came to Rasool Ullah and said: O Rasool Ullah provide for us, help us we want to join.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
لَا اَجِدُ مَا أحمِلُكُمْ عليهَا
I cannot provide you with anything! I don't have anything.
They were so sad that they were deprived from the honor of joining this army
that they left with tears flowing on their cheeks.
So, you can see the contrast here between some people who have wealth and have the ability
and they are happy to stay behind,
فَرِحَ الْمُخَلَّفُونَ
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says: They were happy to stay behind.
And on the other hand, you have these poor Sahabah(صحابه), who eagerly want to go
and when they were prevented, they cried.
So, there's a difference in the hearts here between these and those.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَلَا عَلَى الَّذِينَ إِذَا مَا أَتَوْكَ لِتَحْمِلَهُمْ قُلْتَ لَا أَجِدُ مَا أَحْمِلُكُمْ عَلَيْهِ
تَوَلَّوْا وَأَعْيُنُهُمْ تَفِيضُ مِنَ الدَّمْعِ حَزَنًا أَلَّا يَجِدُوا مَا يُنْفِقُونَ۝
Nor is there blame upon those who, when they came to you, that you might give them mounts, you said;
I can find nothing for you to ride upon.
They turned back while their eyes overflowed with tears out of grief,
that they could not find something to spend for the cause of Allah.
إِنَّمَا السَّبِيلُ عَلَى الَّذِينَ يَسْتَأْذِنُونَكَ وَهُمْ أَغْنِيَاءُ
رَضُوا بِأَنْ يَكُونُوا مَعَ الْخَوَالِفِ وَطَبَعَ اللَّهُ عَلَىٰ قُلُوبِهِمْ فَهُمْ لَا يَعْلَمُونَ۝
The cause for blame is only upon those, who ask permission of you, while they are rich,
they are satisfied to be with those who stay behind
and Allah has sealed over their hearts, so they do not know.
So, Allah said in the previous Ayah(آية) La Yafqahoon(لا يفقهون), they have no Fiqh(فقه).
And in this Ayah(آية)  La Yalamoon(لا يعلمون), they have no knowledge.
So, they have no understanding and they have no knowledge, they don't have either.
Allah says about the Munafiqeen(منافقين).
لو كَانَ عَرَضًا قَرِيبًا وَسَفَرًا قَاصِدًا لَاتَّبَعُوكَ وَلَٰكِنْ
وَلَٰكِنْ بَعُدَتْ عَلَيْهِمُ الشُّقَّةُ
وَسَيَحْلِفُونَ بِاللَّهِ لَوِ اسْتَطَعْنَا لَخَرَجْنَا مَعَكُمْ
يُهْلِكُونَ أَنْفُسَهُمْ وَاللَّهُ يَعْلَمُ إِنَّهُمْ لَكَاذِبُونَ۝
Had it been an easy gain and a moderate trip, meaning if there was a lot of Ghaneemah(غنيمه).
And if the distance wasn't far away, the hypocrites would have followed you.
But distant to them was the journey.
And they will swear by Allah if we were able, we would have gone forth with you.
Destroying themselves through false oaths and Allah knows that indeed, they are liars.
عَفَا اللَّهُ عَنْكَ لِمَ أَذِنْتَ لَهُمْ حَتَّىٰ يَتَبَيَّنَ لَكَ الَّذِينَ صَدَقُوا وَتَعْلَمَ الْكَاذِبِينَ۝
Allah is telling Muhammadﷺ that you should not have excused them, Allah says;
May Allah pardon you, O Muhammad(محمد), why did you give them permission to remain behind?
You should not have, until it was evident to you, who were the truthful,
and you knew, who were the liars.
So, it was a test from Allah.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling Muhammadﷺ that you should not have given them an excuse.
And then Allah tells us who are the true believers, and who are not. Allah says;
لَا يَسْتَأْذِنُكَ الَّذِينَ يُؤْمِنُونَ بِاللَّهِ وَالْيَوْمِ الْآخِرِ أَنْ يُجَاهِدُوا بِأَمْوَالِهِمْ وَأَنْفُسِهِمْ ۗ
وَاللَّهُ عَلِيمٌ بِالْمُتَّقِينَ۝
Those who, believe in Allah, and the last day would not ask permission of you to be excused
from fighting with their wealth and their lives and Allah is knowing of those, who fear Him.
So, the ones who have Taqwa(تقوى) and the ones, who believe in Allah,
they're not going to try to find excuses, but you would find them eager
to support the religion of Allah and fight for it.
But then the ones who are looking for excuses, Allah says about them;
إِنَّمَا يَسْتَأْذِنُكَ الَّذِينَ لَا يُؤْمِنُونَ بِاللَّهِ وَالْيَوْمِ الْآخِرِ وَارْتَابَتْ قُلُوبُهُمْ فَهُمْ
قُلُوبُهُمْ فَهُمْ فِي رَيْبِهِمْ يَتَرَدَّدُونَ۝
Only those would ask permission of you, who do not believe in Allah and the Last Day,
and whose hearts have doubted.
And they are in their doubts are hesitating.
And this is a fact, those who misinterpret the concept of fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
and those who have weak Eeman(ايمان) and try to get out of it.
They are always in a state of hesitation,
they're always in a state of unclarity,
they're in a state of contradiction,
because they say on one hand, that we want to support the religion of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
but then they refused to do it.
And they try to find excuses to get out of it, so it's the contradicting state.
And it's a very changing heart, and Allahعَزّوجَلّ says about them,
they do not have true believe in Allah and the last day,
somebody who has Yaqeen(يقين) in Aakhira(آخرة), and somebody who has true Eeman(ايمان) in Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
first of all, because of the Eeman(ايمان) in Allah,
he will fear Allah more than he fears anybody or anything else.
And because of the Eeman(ايمان) in the last Day, he will not have any value of this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
And then Allah says about them.
And this is a criteria for those who are really excused and those who are not. Allah says;
وَلَوْ أَرَادُوا الْخُرُوجَ لَأَعَدُّوا لَهُ عُدَّةً وَلَٰكِنْ كَرِهَ اللَّهُ انْبِعَاثَهُمْ
وَلَٰكِنْ كَرِهَ اللَّهُ انْبِعَاثَهُمْ فَثَبَّطَهُمْ
فَثَبَّطَهُمْ وَقِيلَ اقْعُدُوا مَعَ الْقَاعِدِينَ۝
And if they had intended to go forth, they would have prepared for it.
Brothers and sisters, anything important needs preparation.
If you want to be a physician, you need to prepare for it, you need to go to school.
If you want to be an engineer, you have to go through years of education.
And same thing in Islam, just like in Duniyah(دنيا), any job or any profession needs a preparation,
otherwise you are lying.
I mean, if somebody says I want to be a doctor, but then he doesn't go to college,
and somebody says I want to find employment, but he never goes and search for it.
Is dishonest with himself.
Same thing in Islam, if you say for example, you want to make Hijrah(هجرة) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), and you don't prepare for it.
You're being dishonest with yourself.
And if you say that you want to strive in the path of Allahعَزّوجَلّ
but you're not doing any preparation for it, then that's also not an excuse
because those, who sincerely want to strive in the cause of Allah are going to prepare
The term preparation is broad, it will include anything that is needed for such a Ibadah(عبادة)
and then Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling Muhammadﷺ that it's better that these people did not come out.
Why? Because this is what they will do.
لَوْ خَرَجُوا فِيكُمْ مَا زَادُوكُمْ إِلَّا خَبَالًا
وَلَأَوْضَعُوا خِلَالَكُمْ يَبْغُونَكُمُ الْفِتْنَةَ وَفِيكُمْ سَمَّاعُونَ لَهُمْ ۗ وَاللَّهُ عَلِيمٌ بِالظَّالِمِينَ۝
Had they gone forth with you, they would not have increased you, except in confusion.
They would not increase you, in anything good.
They would add to the confusion because their minds are full of doubts.
They do not have a firm Yaqeen(يقين) and Eeman(ايمان) in what they're doing.
They're confused, they have so many doubts in their hearts.
They have doubts from the news, they have doubts from the Munafiqeen(منافقين),
they have doubts from the Kuffar(كفار), their minds are full of doubts.
And if they come out with you, they will just add confusion.
And then Allah says and they would have been active among you.
Active with what?
Seeking to cause you Fitnah(فِتْنَه), they're going to come out for the cause of Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
They're going to come out with Nameema(نميمة), backbiting, they're going to try
to cause disunity among you, they will spread their doubts among your ranks,
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ says and among you are avid listeners to them,
Allah is knowing of the wrongdoers.
Who's Allah speaking to?
He is speaking to the generation of the Sahabah(صحابه).
Allah is telling them and among you are avid listeners to them.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) how could a companion be an avid listener of a Munafiq(منافق)?
Well, that's the whole point behind the importance of warning against the Munafiqeen(منافقين)
because they are so elusive, it's very difficult to tell, who a Munafiq(منافق) is?
Because they could be very sweet tongue,
they could be very knowledgeable,
they could be very prominent,
they could be very charismatic,
they could have such a captivating personality.
And you look up to them, and you listen to their words.
And their words make sense to you.
And that's why you become an avid listener to them.
And in reality, they are deceiving you,
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ is giving this warning to the Sahabah(صحابه).
So, what do you think about us today?
How much confusion are these Munafiqeen(منافقين) causing us today?
When we are very far away from the understanding of the Sahabah(صحابه),
when our Fitrah(فطرة) is corrupted because the Sahabah(صحابه) had a clean Fitrah(فطرة).
I mean for them, because of their clean Fitrah(فطرة),
they would have a better ability in distinguishing what is right from wrong.
However, with us living in such a corrupt material world,
where the values and the norms that we are brought up with, are so messed up.
The confusion is even worse.
And that is why, you find that a wide section of the Ummah(امة) is really confused.
They don't know what they're supposed to do?
They don't know what their duties are.?
They're in state of loss.
Brothers and sisters is very important to study the Ayaat(آيات) of Surah At-Taubah(سورة التوبة)
and study the Ayaat(آيات) of Munafiqeen(منافقين) in Ayaat Ut-Taubah(آيات التوبة),
so that we could be cautious from two things.
Number one, that we are not Munafiqeen(منافقين) ourselves.
And number two, that we do not fall into or not fooled by the ones, who are Munafiqeen(منافقين).
I mean, Nifaaq(نفاق) is such a delicate thing and very elusive thing, that
even Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه used to fear that he might be a Munafiq(منافق).
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) Umar(عمر) and he would go to Hudaifah(حديفه), the one, who had the secret of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and he knew the names of the Munafiqeen(منافقين).
He went to him and he said: I ask you in the name of Allah,
Did Rasool Ullah mentioned me among the Munafiqeen(منافقين).?
Hudaifah(حديفه) told him: No. And I'm not gonna answer this question to anyone other than you.
Because it's secret and Hudaifah(حديفه) did not want to give it up.
And so Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling the Muslims that is better than they didn't come out
because if they came out, they're not really into fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
They don't understand fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
and therefore they're going to come out and just cause confusion amongst you.
لَقَدِ ابْتَغَوُا الْفِتْنَةَ مِنْ قَبْلُ وَقَلَّبُوا لَكَ الْأُمُورَ
وَقَلَّبُوا لَكَ الْأُمُورَ حَتَّىٰ جَاءَ الْحَقُّ وَظَهَرَ أَمْرُ اللَّهِ وَهُمْ كَارِهُونَ۝
They had already desired destination before, and had upset matters for you, until the truth came,
and the ordinance of Allah appeared, while they were averse,
Abdullah Bin Ubae(عبدالله بن أبي) such a despised individual.
We all hate him because we know that he is a Munafiq(منافق).
But let's put things in the right context
Abdullah Bin Ubae(عبدالله بن أبي) was the leader of his people, he was Sayed Al-Kharaj(سيدالخزرج),
he was the lord of Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج), their chief
and Abdullah Bin Ubae(عبدالله بن أبي) used to stand before Rasool Allah ﷺ, when he would give Khutba tul Jummah(خطبة الجمعه).
And tell the people that Muhammadﷺ is the Messenger of Allah, so listen to his words.
I mean, he is standing in front of the people before the Khut'bah(خطبه), introducing the Khut'ba(خطبه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, telling people to listen to him.
And when Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) told Rasool Allah ﷺ that we should kill him,
Rasool Allah ﷺ mentions in one narration,
سَتَرْغَم لَه’ اُنُفْ
There are many men, who might fight for him.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), Abdullah Bin Ubae(عبدالله بن أبي), had a great following,
and some of the people who are deceived by him might not handle it well,
and that's why Rasool Allah ﷺ refused to execute him.
So, these were prominent members in the society,
and they have caused such dissension among the Muslims and problems in the past,
as Allahعزوَجل says, in the Ayah(آية), I just recited,
وَمِنْهُمْ مَنْ يَقُولُ ائْذَنْ لِي وَلَا تَفْتِنِّي ۚ أَلَا فِي الْفِتْنَةِ سَقَطُوا ۗ
وَإِنَّ جَهَنَّمَ لَمُحِيطَةٌ بِالْكَافِرِينَ۝
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Al-Jadd Bin Qais(الجد بن قيس) and he is one of the leaders of Al-Munafiqeen(ألمنافقين)
he told him, are you ready for fighting the Romans?
Al-Jadd Bin Qais(الجد بن قيس) said;
O Messenger Of Allah my people know, I have a reputation of being a man, who loves women so much,
and I fear for myself, if I go with you, that I might fall into Fitnah(فِتْنَه),
because of the women of the women of Bannu Asfar(بنو الاصفر),
Bannu Asfar(بنو الاصفر) is the name that is given to the Romans, Asfar(أصفر) is yellow.
So, the children of Asfar(أصفر) or the people that are yellow,
that was the color that was was given to them as their description.
So, Al-Jadd Bin Qais(الجد بن قيس) is saying;
If I go to you, the women over there are going to cause me Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
So, the reason why he wanted to stay, behind is to stay away from Fitnah(فِتْنَه)
which you can see that he gave himself an excuse,
as if it is for the sake of Allah, you know, I don't want to go out and fight
because it's going to cause me Fitnah(فِتْنَه), I might fall into Haram(حرام).
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَمِنْهُمْ مَنْ يَقُولُ ائْذَنْ لِي وَلَا تَفْتِنِّي ۚ أَلَا فِي الْفِتْنَةِ سَقَطُوا
And among them is he, who says permit me to remain at home and do not put me to trial.
Trial here is translation of Fitnah(فِتْنَه),
unquestionably into trial they have fallen.
And indeed, hell will encompass the disbelievers.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling us that by staying behind you're staying in Fitnah(فِتْنَه),
if you go, you will be spared Fitnah(فِتْنَه), if you stay behind, then you're in Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
So, the ones who always talk about the excuse that I'm not prepared spiritually,
I'm not prepared this or that, they will never be prepared spiritually
if they stay behind because they're always going to be in a state of Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
It is when they go out Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) that they will be free of the Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
And that's why Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَالَّذِينَ جَاهَدُوا فِينَا لَنَهْدِيَنَّهُمْ سُبُلَنَا
The ones, who are struggling in our cause Allah will guide them, to Our paths.
So, guidance comes with going out. Allahعَزّوجَلّ your says about the Al-Munafiqeen(ألمنافقين).
إِنْ تُصِبْكَ حَسَنَةٌ تَسُؤْهُمْ ۖ
وَإِنْ تُصِبْكَ مُصِيبَةٌ يَقُولُوا قَدْ أَخَذْنَا أَمْرَنَا مِنْ قَبْلُ وَيَتَوَلَّوْا وَهُمْ فَرِحُونَ۝
If good befalls you, it distresses them
but if disaster strikes you they say we took our matter in hand before and turned away while they are rejoicing.
This is another habits of the Al-Munafiqeen(ألمنافقين), they are happy when disaster befalls the Muslims.
And when that happens and they stayed behind they would say;
See we told you, why did you go out?
And they think that they are wise because they avoided trouble
and it's actually the opposite, they are falling into trouble.
And then Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
قُلْ هَلْ تَرَبَّصُونَ بِنَا إِلَّا إِحْدَى الْحُسْنَيَيْنِ ۖ
وَنَحْنُ نَتَرَبَّصُ بِكُمْ أَنْ يُصِيبَكُمُ اللَّهُ بِعَذَابٍ مِنْ عِنْدِهِ أَوْ بِأَيْدِينَا ۖ
فَتَرَبَّصُوا إِنَّا مَعَكُمْ مُتَرَبِّصُونَ۝
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says; Say do you await for us except, one of the two best things.
What are the two best things.?
Either victory or martyrdom.
While we await for you
that Allahعَزّوجَلّ will afflict you with punishment from himself or at our hands.
So, wait indeed we along you are waiting.
So, wait indeed we along with you are waiting.
So, the Muslim should tell the Al-Munafiqeen(ألمنافقين).
that whatever happens to us, even if we defeated, even if we lose,
and you think that you're wise and smart that you stayed behind,
you need to understand that our objective is one of two things, either victory or martyrdom.
And these are the best things to wait for.
While we are waiting for also two things to happen to you
either a punishment from Allah or a punishment from us.
So, these are some Ayaat(آيات) that we're talking about
the ones who stayed behind in the Battle of Tabook(تبوك).
In Sha Allah ho Ta'ala(اِن ْشاء الله تعالى) we'll carry on in our next session.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته